var array = [{question: "2011.NatsBowl.1 Prior to this battle, one side opened up a key supply route called the Cracker Line and defeated an enemy force at Wauhatchie. During its beginning, General George Thomas was able to quickly take Orchard Knob. In the aftermath of this battle, Joseph Johnston replaced Braxton Bragg as the head of a large army. Lookout Mountain and (*) Missionary Ridge were two defensive structures during this battle whose aftermath saw an assault on Atlanta. For 10 points, name this November 1863 battle of the American Civil War fought several months after the Battle of Chickamagua, a Union victory in southeastern Tennessee.", ANSWER: "Chattanooga"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.3 Because he was delayed in the Battle of Rosebud, George Crook could not participate in this battle. Frederick Benteen provided backup for Marcus Reno on what is now known as Reno Hill during this battle. One of the few survivors on the losing side of this battle was named Curly, and his report of this battle differs from that of Chief Gall. (*) Buffalo Calf Road Woman is credited with knocking the American commander off his horse. This 1876 battle of the Great Sioux War resulted in a decisive victory for the side led by Crazy Horse. For 10 points, name this battle nicknamed “Custer’s Last Stand.”", ANSWER: "Little Bighorn"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.5 Jacklyn Lucas became the youngest man since the Civil War to receive a Medal of Honor for his heroism in this battle. During this battle, the Bismarck Sea was sunk during a kamikaze attack. Men like Ira Hayes and John Bradley became famous for their participation in this battle thanks to (+) Joe Rosenthal. Ground fighting during this battle was prolonged due to Tadamichi Kuribayashi prohibiting banzai charges, and that commander also ordered an extensive series of tunnels to be dug. Some of the heaviest fighting in this battle took place on Meatgrinder Hill and Mount (*) Suribachi. For 10 points, name this early 1945 battle in the Pacific Theatre of World War II on a “God-forsaken island”, where several Marines famously raised a US flag.", ANSWER: "Iwo Jima"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.9 One supply line in this battle came to be known as the Sacred Way for its use in this battle. A costly strategic blow to one side in this battle was the loss of Fort Douaumont. The French were ultimately able to reclaim that fort under the leadership of Philippe Petain, though its loss had resulted in 100,000 casualties. For 10 points, name this bloody battle of World War I that ran from February to December of 1916.", ANSWER: "Verdun"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.11 Seven years before this battle, the death of Yohannes IV led to one participant helping the forces of Shewa to take the throne. This battle settled a conflict that began due to Prime Minister Crispi’s interpretation of Article Seventeen of the Treaty of Wichale. Oreste Bartieri lost to Menelik II and made peace at the Treaty of Addis Ababa following, for 10 points, what 1896 battle in which Ethiopia turned back an Italian force?", ANSWER: "Adowa"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.11 The brother of one man killed at this battle was named Tostig, and himself was killed weeks before this battle. One force in this battle was initially deployed on Senlac Hill, and one battle that preceded this one was at (+) Gate Fulford, while another took place north of the site of this battle and featured an invading force led by Harald Hardraada of Norway. That battle, Stamford Bridge, had weakened one side in this conflict, who were led by (*) Harold Godwinson, and this battle is famously depicted by the Bayeux Tapestry. For 10 points, name this 1066 battle in which Harold's English force was defeated by the Norman army of William the Conqueror.", ANSWER: "Hastings"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.12 One side in this battle was supplied in part by a group of troops who ran the Red Ball Express. An offensive launched by the other side in this battle was Operation Bodenplatte, and that side in this battle also launched a surprise attack on the ghost front. For 10 points, name this 1944-1945 battle fought in the Ardennes Mountains, in which the Germans were ultimately repulsed despite causing a temporary namesake deformation in the Allied line.", ANSWER: "Bulge"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.12 In this battle, the Duke of Brabant arrived late from a christening and was killed because he hastily made an unrecognizable tabard from a flag. The winner ordered his men to lance their prisoners at the end of this battle, which was preceded by the siege of Harfleur. The losers managed to steal a crown from the baggage train of one of the victors before their commander, (*) Charles d'Albert, led them headlong into a line of pikes driven into the deep mud. The superiority of the Welsh longbow was also critical to the success of Henry V. Fought in 1415 on St. Crispin's Day, for 10 points, name this turning point of the Hundred Years' War.", ANSWER: "Agincourt"},
             {question: "2011.NatsBowl.18 This battle led to a treaty that was signed in the palace of Bratislava, the Peace of Pressburg. The turning point of this battle came when the attackers captured the Pratzen Heights. This battle led to the dissolution of the Holy Roman Empire. For 10 points, name this December 1805 battle in which Napoleon divided his army against a larger force and still beat the combined forces of Russia and Austria.", ANSWER: "Austerlitz"},
             {question: "2011.CBowl.6 One force at this battle organized in a formation similar to a phalanx that had densely wooded forests on each of their flanks. The cavalry of the opposing side in this battle returned to their camp after a rumor about looting treasure from Bordeaux. The Umayyads at this battle were commanded by Abd al-Rahman. For 10 points, name this 732 battle where Charles Martel halted Muslim expansion in Europe.", ANSWER: "Tours"},
             {question: "2011.CBowl.10 The outcome of this battle was made possible by the comte de Grasse's victory in the Battle of the Chesapeake, which made the British unable to lift the siege led by Rochambeau and Washington. For 10 points, name this last major battle of the Revolutionary War that saw Cornwallis surrender to Washington.", ANSWER: "Yorktown"},
             {question: "2011.CBowl.10 Immediately before this battle, William Halsey suffered a bout of psoriasis, leading him to be replaced by Raymond A. Spruance. The JN-25 code was broken before this battle, during which the Enterprise and Hornet emerged victorious over the Kaga and Akagi. For 10 points, name this 1942 allied naval victory in World War II.", ANSWER: "Midway"},
             {question: "2011.CBowl.10 In this battle, Joshua Chamberlain’s Maine infantry led a bayonet charge at Little Round Top.(+) The end of this battle came shortly after the failure of a charge on Cemetery Ridge (*) led by George Pickett. For 10 points, name this three day 1863 battle in Pennsylvania often considered the “high water mark” of the Confederacy.", ANSWER: "Gettysburg"},
             {question: "2011.CBee.1 This battle was preceded by fighting at Quatre-Bras and Ligny. During this battle, the farm of Le Haye Sainte was captured by Marshall Ney, and the arrival of Prussian troops under von Blucher secured victory for the Duke of Wellington’s forces. This battle marked the end of the Hundred Days. For the point, name this final defeat of Napoleon.", ANSWER: "Waterloo"},
             {question: "2011.CBee.2 Light infantry commander Lord Balcarres surrendered during this battle. One of Daniel Morgan's snipers killed Simon Fraser during this battle. A British victory at Freeman's Farm was undone by their loss at Bemis Heights here. For the point, name this Revolutionary War battle that saw the defeat of John Burgoyne by Horatio Gates and Benedict Arnold.", ANSWER: "Saratoga"},
             {question: "2011.CBee.2 Before this battle, the winners cracked the JN-25 code. The Hornet sunk the Mikuma in this battle, during which the Hiryu airplanes sunk the USS Yorktown. It occurred a month after the Battle of Coral Sea. For the point, name this decisive battle of the Pacific Theater of World War II, fought near a namesake atoll.", ANSWER: "Midway"},
             {question: "2011.BBowl.2 Sites during this battle included Freeman's Farm and Bemis Heights. During this battle, forces under Horatio Gates and Benedict Arnold forced the surrender of John Burgoyne. For 10 points, name this revolutionary campaign in New York, an American victory that brought France into the war.", ANSWER: "Saratoga"},
             {question: "2011.BBowl.8 This battle's location is now combined with Des Braves Park as Battlefields Park. This battle was the first major engagement following the fall of Louisbourg. Both the Marquis de Montcalm and General James Wolfe died during this battle on the Plains of Abraham. For 10 points, name this 1759 British victory that led to the capture of Montreal.", ANSWER: "Quebec"},
             {question: "2011.BBee.2 This battle was preceded by the Battle of Lake Borgne, in which Alexander Cochrane led his fleet to the city of this battle. Jean Lafitte's pirates helped the winning side in this battle. General Edward Pakenham died during this battle. For the point, name this battle that occurred after the official end of the War of 1812, a victory for Andrew Jackson.", ANSWER: "New Orleans"},
             {question: "2011.BBee.2 Prior to this battle's end, Albert Martin led thirty-two men from DeWitt Colony to aid one side. That side in this battle was led by William Travis, who fought with a force that included James Bowie and Davy Crockett. For the point, name this 1836 battle in which the Mexican force under Santa Anna wiped out the defenders of a San Antonio mission.", ANSWER: "Alamo"},
             {question: "2011.BBee.3 This battle saw one side attempt the Sinyavino Offensive, which threw off the timing of their enemies, who were at the time planning Operation Nordlicht. This battle saw a Road of Life of supplies ferried across Lake Ladoga. For the point, name this World War II battle that was a lengthy siege of a Russian city now known as St. Petersburg.", ANSWER: "Leningrad"},
             {question: "2011.BBee.4 The losing general in this battle split forces under Frederick Benteen and Marcus Reno from the main army. A horse named Comanche was the only survivor on one side of this battle, in which five companies of the Seventh Cavalry was lost. For the point, name this 1876 battle in which the Lakota Sioux under Sitting Bull ensured George Custer's Last Stand.", ANSWER: "Little Bighorn"},
             {question: "2011.BBee.5 The losers in this battle were weakened by winning the Battle of Stamford Bridge a few weeks prior. This battle actually occurred at Senlac Hill. The Bayeux Tapestry is a depiction of this battle, which ended with Harold Godwinson's death. For the point, name this battle that occurred in 1066 and allowed William the Conqueror to become King of England.", ANSWER: "Hastings"},
             {question: "2011.BBee.5 Nathanael Greene's defeat at Guilford Court House directly led to this battle. Admiral de Grasse's defeat of the British Navy and blockade of the Chesapeake Bay was critical to the American victory in this battle. For the point, name this last major battle of the Revolutionary War in which Lord Cornwallis surrendered to George Washington.", ANSWER: "Yorktown"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.1 Prior to this battle, George Crook's men had been surprised and defeated at the Battle of the Rosebud. This battle's outset saw the charge of Marcus Reno turn into a rout when his left flank was turned by forces under Gall. That force was only saved by reinforcements under Frederick Bendeen. This battle ended with five companies of the Seventh Cavalry being completely destroyed. For 10 points, name this 1876 battle that saw Sitting Bull and Crazy Horse's Sioux and Cheyenne force annihilate forces under George Custer.", ANSWER: "Little Bighorn"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.1 In the aftermath of this battle, Uluch Ali managed to salvage most of his forces from harm. Miguel de Cervantes lost use of an arm during this battle. During this battle, the half-brother of Philip II, Don John of Austria, commanded the forces of the Holy League. For 10 points, name this 1571 naval battle which ended Ottoman dominance in the Mediterranean.", ANSWER: "Lepanto"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.3 In this battle, Joseph Hooker's corps was unable to capture Dunker Church. After Burnside captured a stone bridge, A.P. Hill arrived with reinforcements from (+) Harpers Ferry, ending this battle. Fighting also occurred on a sunken road called Bloody Lane during this battle, before which the Union discovered Special Order 191, part of the Confederate plans, wrapped around some cigars. (*) McClellan's failure to pursue the Confederates after this battle led to his removal from command. The outcome of this battle led Lincoln to issue the Emancipation Proclamation. For 10 points, name this bloodiest day of the Civil War, an 1862 battle in Maryland.", ANSWER: "Antietam"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.4 During this battle, a farmhouse called La Haye Sainte was captured by the Old Guard commander Michel Ney. The losing side's right flank was attacked at this battle by Gebhard von Bluecher, ultimately leading to the defeated commander's exile to Saint Helena. For 10 points, name this 1815 battle in which Napoleon was defeated by the Duke of Wellington.", ANSWER: "Waterloo"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.4 The leader of one side in this battle agreed to a request made by Cardinal Talleyrand to hold his troops back on a Sunday. That leader, Jean le Bon, followed the advice of William Douglas to fight on foot, and was captured in this battle by forces under Edward, the Black Prince. For 10 points, name this 1356 victory for the English in the Hundred Years' War.", ANSWER: "Poitiers"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.4 One site at this battle was held after a bayonet charge by the Twentieth Maine, which was led by Joshua Chamberlain. This battle saw a futile march under heavy fire occur during an attack on Cemetery Ridge called Pickett’s Charge. For 10 points, name this three day 1863 battle in which Robert E. Lee’s invasion was stopped by George Meade in Pennsylvania.", ANSWER: "Gettysburg"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.5 One rail fence in this battle was held for a time by four hundred militia commanded by John Stark. One side landed for this battle at Moulton's Point, and this battle saw the death of Joseph Warren. William Prescott and Israel Putnam, the losing commanders of this battle, have both been credited with ordering, don't fire until you see the whites of their eyes. For 10 points, name this 1775 strategic loss but moral victory for the U.S. fought on Breeds Hill near Boston.", ANSWER: "Bunker Hill"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.7 One side in this battle landed at Pevensey before moving to this battle's site. This battle took place in Battle, seven miles from its namesake town. Before this battle, its first casualty, the bard Taillefer, juggled swords and sang the Song of Roland. One side in this battle was on Senlac Hill, and had won against Harald Hardrada at Stamford Bridge. This battle is depicted in the Bayeux Tapestry. For 10 points, name this 1066 loss for Harold Godwinson during William the Conqueror's Norman invasion of England.", ANSWER: "Hastings"},
             {question: "2011.ABowl.8 One commander at this battle, Henry Percy, refused to move his forces when signaled, and another leader of forces for that side was John Howard. Thomas and William Stanley initially remained unengaged at this battle, but encircled and killed Richard III, leaving Henry Tudor the victor. For 10 points, name this battle that closed the Wars of the Roses.", ANSWER: "Bosworth Field"},
             {question: "2011.ABee.2 During this battle, the Comte de Grasse prevented a relief effort by Thomas Graves by defeating him at the Battle of the Chesapeake. This battle’s victors had marched down from New York to besiege a general retreating from North Carolina after the Battle of Guilford Courthouse. The defeated force’s band played “The World Turned Upside Down” while surrendering at this battle. For the point, name this defeat for Lord Cornwallis which ended the Revolutionary War.", ANSWER: "Yorktown"},
             {question: "2011.ABee.3 The first part of this battle was fought at Freeman's Farm. Later fighting as part of this battle was fought at Bemis Heights and led to the defeat of a General who had waited for eighteen days before this battle to allow his lengthy baggage train to meet his forces. News of this battle led Louis XVI to negotiate a French alliance with the victorious colonists. For the point, name this 1777 battle in upstate New York.", ANSWER: "Saratoga"},
             {question: "2011.ABee.4 The Battles of Wavre and Ligny were two battles that preceded this battle. One commander at this battle formed up his men on Mont Saint-Jean ridge to prevent access to Belgium. The French commander at this battle sent his younger brother Jerome to attack the farm house of Hougoumont which anchored the British right flank. The turn of this battle was when the Prussian army arrived to relieve the faltering British soldiers under the Duke of Wellington. For the point, name this final defeat for Napoleon.", ANSWER: "Waterloo"},
             {question: "2011.ABee.4 An attempt to conclude this battle ended when the Italian 8th Army was defeated, threatening Erich von Manstein’s flank. The turning point at this battle came with the launching of Operation Uranus, which encircled the attackers in this battle. An attempt to supply those attackers by air was only able to provide them with starvation rations and the promotion of Friedrich Paulus to Field Marshal was unable to prevent him from surrendering the 9th Army the next day. For the point, name this 1942-43 battle, the siege of a Russian city considered a major turning point of World War II.", ANSWER: "Stalingrad"},
             {question: "2011.ABee.4 This battle’s victors marched to it a month after besieging Harfleur. The Treaty of Troyes was signed after this battle, in which a row of sharpened wooden stakes planted in the mud protected against cavalry charge so that Thomas Erpingham’s longbowmen could fire. Charles d’Albret was killed commanding the losing side of this battle, which took place on Saint Crispin’s Day. For the point, name this 1415 victory of Henry V of England over the French.", ANSWER: "Agincourt"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBowl.5 One commander in this battle famously proclaimed, We are in the chamber pot and about to be shat upon. General Ducrot took command partway through this battle, but his order to retreat was overruled by General de Wimpffen. This battle was preceded by the Battle of Beaumont and a failure to lift the Siege of (+) Metz. Moltke the Elder split his forces into three groups, allowing him to encircle the opposing army. Patrice de MacMahon led the Army of Chalons to defeat in this battle. (*) Napoleon III was captured as a result of this battle, thereby effectively deciding the war in favor of Prussia. For 10 points, name this 1870 battle of the Franco-Prussian War.", ANSWER: "Sedan"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBowl.7 One noble at this battle, the Earl of Northumberland, chose not to aid his king at a critical moment. The intervention of Thomas and William Stanley was critical in this battle, in which Richard of York was killed, marking the end of the Plantagenet dynasty. For 10 points, identify this battle at which Henry Tudor was victorious, ending the Wars of the Roses.", ANSWER: "Bosworth Field"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBowl.9 Notable combatants in this battle included the future Hero of Bennington, John Stark, and Daniel Shays. John Trumbull commemorated the Death of General Warren at this battle, in which the British won a Pyrrhic victory by gaining the (+) Charlestown peninsula at the expense of numerous officers and a third of their forces. Occurring on July 17, 1775 during the Siege of (*) Boston, the majority of the fighting in it actually occurred on Breed's Hill. For 10 points, name this battle of the American Revolution during which either Israel Putnam or William Prescott saying, Don't fire until you see the whites of their eyes.", ANSWER: "Bunker Hill"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBowl.10 In the aftermath of this battle, Abraham Lincoln responded to criticism of one general with the quote, I can't spare this man; he fights. Brigadier general W. H. L. Wallace's men held a position known as the Hornet's Nest in this battle, along a path called the Sunken Road. Reinforcements under Don Carlos Buell turned the tide on the second day of this then-bloodiest Civil War battle. For 10 points, identify this April 6-7, 1862 victory for Union forces under Grant, fought in southern Tennessee.", ANSWER: "Shiloh"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBowl.16 A part of the larger campaign to capture Russia’s main Black Sea naval base, it followed the Allied victory at the Battle of Alma. The 93rd Highland Regiment of Sutherland Highlanders formed the Thin Red Line of this battle and repelled a Russian cavalry charge. For 10 points, name the battle of the Crimean War that featured the Charge of the Light Brigade.", ANSWER: "Balaclava"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBowl.16 Following this battle, the losers at the battle of Fulford, Morcar and Edwin, threw their support behind Edgar the Atheling. This battle began when a man singing the Song of Roland, Taillefer, killed an English soldier. Leofwine and Gryth both died at this battle along with their brother who was shot in the eye with an arrow. The Bayeux Tapestry depicts, for 10 points, what defeat of Harold Godwinson by William the Conqueror?", ANSWER: "Hastings"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBowl.17 During this battle, ships under Operation MO moved through the Jomard Passage. Frank Fletcher's forces won a strategic victory despite suffering heavier losses against Admiral Inouye's fleet. Despite the loss of the (+) Lexington, the winning side in this battle prevented the Shokaku and Zuikaku carriers from being available for the battle of Midway the following month. The fighting in this battle was entirely done by (*) planes since enemy ships never made contact. For 10 points, name this May 1942 Allied victory over Japan that prevented the capture of New Guinea.", ANSWER: "Coral Sea"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.1 This battle took place at its location due to the burning of Stoddert's Bridge and the Eastern Branch Bridge, but Tobias Stansbury's orders to destroy a bridge leading from Lowndes Hill were ignored. A monument at this battle's site honors Joshua Barney, who was shot in the leg while his Marines were the only part of the losing side to hold their ground. Robert Ross commanded the winning side, and James Madison is said to have briefly commanded one battery before William Winder ordered a disorganized militia retreat that turned into this battle's namesake races. For the point, name this 1814 British victory that paved the way for the burning of Washington, D.C.", ANSWER: "Bladensburg"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.2 This battle was fought largely along the Maumee River; at its end, one side retreated to a fort but was refused entry by the British. This battle was the culmination of a conflict that saw forces under Arthur St. Clair massacred. Prior to this battle, a group partially led by Little Turtle decided not to attack Fort Recovery, since the opposing commander never sleeps. A confederacy dominated by Buckongahelas and Blue Jacket was defeated at this battle, which led to the Treaty of Greenville granting much of Ohio to the United States. For the point, name this 1794 victory for Mad Anthony Wayne over a Native American force that tried to defend themselves behind a group of dislodged trees.", ANSWER: "Fallen Timbers"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.2 One song about this battle states, tis not often you see a hunter from Kentucky, despite the fact that the Kentucky militiamen fled from an assault led by Colonel Thornton. After this battle, Admiral Cochrane captured Fort Bowyer and one side laid siege to Fort St. Philip. Following this battle, over 200 ex-slaves were taken to Bermuda by General Lambert. Much of this battle was fought on the Chalmette plantation with the aid of the Laffite brothers. Prior to this battle, a treaty negotiated by Castlereagh (castle-ray) was signed that ended the war of which this battle was a part. For the point, name this victory for Andrew Jackson and last major engagement of the War of 1812.", ANSWER: "New Orleans"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.3 At this battle, the Frenchman Monsieur Sinfray fought for the losers, who were gunned down on the first rainy night after forgetting to cover their gunpowder. Prior to this battle, the Treaty of Alinagar allowed the victors to trade duty-free in a certain province with permits called dastak. The Irishman Eyre Coote and the factory owner William Watts fought for this battle’s victors, who convinced Mir Jafar to defect to their side. The raid on Fort William and the Black Hole of Calcutta preceded this battle, a defeat for Siraj ad-Daula, the Nawab of Bengal. For the point, name this 1757 victory for Robert Clive and the British East India Company.", ANSWER: "Plassey"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.3 On the night before this battle, when a commander went amongst his soldiers to observe their behavior, they lit their straw bedding to guide him back to his tent. The victor at this battle killed many retreating forces by having his soldiers shoot the ice they fled over. That commander deliberately abandoned a plateau before this battle, allowing Nicolas Soult to charge up the plateau and destroy the enemy's center; that plateau was the Pratzen Heights. The losers at this battle were forced to sign the Treaty of Pressburg, which created the Confederation of the Rhine. For the point, name this 1805 battle in the modern-day Czech Republic, where Napoleon defeated Francis II and Alexander I.", ANSWER: "Austerlitz"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.3 A decisive point in this battle occurred when Dabormida's right flank was attacked by a force led by Ras Makonnen. Seven years prior to this battle, the Treaty of Wichale was signed, but one side presented an alternate version of the treaty afterwards. Taking place in the region of Tigray, this battle began with a night attack by the losers, which ended in that army becoming disorganized, dealing Oreste Baratieri a huge defeat. For the point, name this 1896 battle in which Emperor Menelik II kept Ethiopia independent by defeating the Italians.", ANSWER: "Adowa"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.5 Polish participation in this battle included the 302 “Ponznanski” and 303 “Kosciusko” groups, and one side launched its attach after issuing Directive 17. Keith Park commanded the No 11 group during this battle, phases of which included “Eagle Attack” and the Channel battles. One side was commanded by Hugh Dowding. The winning of this battle signaled the abandonment of Operation Sea Lion by one side, and at the end of this battle one leader stated that “never in the field of human conflict was so much owed by so many to so few”, referring to the RAF. During this battle, one side launched the Blitz, a sustained 76-day bombing campaign over London. For the point, name this battle in which the Luftwaffe was repulsed from the skies above the UK.", ANSWER: "Britain"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.6 The collision of the ships Mogami and Miguma during this battle occurred as a result of the sighting of the submarine Tambor. One leader in this battle moved his command to the ship Astoria after he abandoned his old command, which was later sunk by a submarine. That old command absorbed two attacks, leading the other side to believe that they had sunk two carriers when in fact they had only damaged the Yorktown. For the point, name this 1942 naval battle in which the Japanese lost four carriers and failed to take the namesake Pacific island.", ANSWER: "Midway"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.Finals The hill Mamayev Kurgan changed hands multiple times during this battle and contains a memorial to it today. One side attempted to counteract other’s firepower by staying as close to them as possible, a strategy called “hugging” the enemy. Vasily Zaytsev was a sniper who killed 225 enemy soldiers during this battle. One heavily armed fortification in this battle was known as “Pavlov’s House.” Operation Uranus resulted in the encirclement of one side in this battle. Friedrich Paulus surrendered at the end of this battle, which resulted in the complete destruction of the German Sixth Army. For the point, name this battle of World War II, a 1942-43 fight for control of a city in southern Russia.", ANSWER: "Stalingrad"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.Finals In this battle, a contingent outnumbered four-to-one under Joachim Murat was able to repel a clumsy initial attack, and this battle saw the death of Jozef Poniatowski after confused troops in retreat blew up the lone bridge across the Elster. The winning side in this battle received reinforcements on October 17 from Count von Bennigsen and Jean Bernadotte. The day prior, the loser repelled the attacks of forces from the south under Karl Philipp Schwarzenberg and from the north under Gebhard von Blücher. For the point, name this 1813 battle in which Napoleon was defeated by a coalition of Swedish, Russian, Prussian, and Austrian forces at a city in Saxony.", ANSWER: "Leipzig"},
             {question: "2012.NatsBee.Finals Immediately after this battle, a group of 47 nobles were executed in the “Day of Blood”. One side’s forces were commanded by Christian of Arnhaldt, while another commander here was eventually killed at the siege of Nove Zamkey, the Count of Boquoy. This battle, which Rene Descartes participated in, was the final event in a campaign that began when Emperor Matthias’ delegates Slavata of Chulm and Borzita of Maurice were thrown out of a window by Jindrich Thurn. After this battle, Elizabeth Stuart and her husband ran away, earning that ruler the name “Winter King”. For the point, name this 1620 battle in which Count Tilly put down a Bohemian revolt on behalf of Frederick V at a site just outside Prague.", ANSWER: "White Mountain"},
             {question: "2012.CBowl.4 The results of this battle halted the offensive Case Blue, which was meant to capture oil fields. The turning point of this battle was Operation Uranus, and one side was led by General Friedrich Paulus. This bloody battle on the Volga resulted in a Soviet victory over Nazis. For 10 points, identify this turning point on the Eastern Front during World War II, taking place in a Russian city named for a Soviet dictator.", ANSWER: "Stalingrad"},
             {question: "2012.CBowl.6 Before this battle, the HMS Lively fired on one side's half-constructed redoubt before being repudiated by Samuel Graves. George Clinton proposed an alternative strategy attacking Charlestown Neck before this battle. Joseph Warren was killed in the retreat from the main site of this battle, where Israel (+) Putnam led troops from Connecticut. This battle occurred north of Boston, across (*) Copp's Hill. For 10 points, name this early battle of the American Revolution, mostly fought on Breed's Hill, rather than its namesake hill.", ANSWER: "Bunker Hill"},
             {question: "2012.CBee.3 Near the end of this battle, the defenders failed to withdraw to Gloucester point after redoubts nine and ten fell. The defeat of Thomas Graves by the Comte de Grasse cut off supplies before this battle where the Comte de Rochambeau and George Washington forced Lord Cornwallis to surrender. For the point, name this last major battle of the American Revolution fought on a namesake peninsula.", ANSWER: "Yorktown"},
             {question: "2012.CBee.3 During this battle, General Bauduin was killed during an engagement at Hougoumont, and this battle also included fighting at Plancenoit. This battle was preceded by the Battle of Ligny, and Prussian troops were commanded by Gebhard von Blucher during this battle. This battle took place at the end of the Hundred Days of the losing commander, who had come back from Elba. For the point, identify this 1815 victory for the Duke of Wellington in Belgium, which was Napoleon's final defeat.", ANSWER: "Waterloo"},
             {question: "2012.CBee.7 This battle was preceded by one at Brandy Station, and it began with a clash between the forces of Henry Heth and John Buford near Cashtown. Joshua Chamberlain ordered a bayonet charge on Little Round Top in this battle, which also saw fighting on Cemetery Ridge. Ending with Pickett's Charge, this battle was a victory for George Mead over Robert E. Lee. For the point, name this July 1863 battle in Pennsylvania.", ANSWER: "Gettysburg"},
             {question: "2012.CBee.7 One side in this battle was delayed while waiting for Robert Lloyd's fleet from the Battle of Fayal. During this engagement, a flooded canal prevented William Thornton from supporting John Keane, who camped east of this battle's location after the Battle of Lake Borgne. The British seized Fort St. Philip after this battle, during which they were led by Edward Pakenham and Alexander Cochrane. This battle occurred several weeks after the Treaty of Ghent was signed. For the point, name this victory for Andrew Jackson in Louisiana during the War of 1812.", ANSWER: "New Orleans"},
             {question: "2012.BBowl.1 At this battle, Edward 'Allegheny' Johnson led the Confederate charge on Culp's Hill. John Wheeler was killed in this battle while defending Devil's Den. Strong Vincent and Joseph Chamberlain, who led the 20th Maine, helped defend Little Round Top in this battle. The northernmost point of the Union line at this battle was Cemetery Hill. For 10 points, George Meade repulsed Robert E. Lee's invasion of Pennsylvania at what bloodiest battle of the Civil War?", ANSWER: "Gettysburg"},
             {question: "2012.BBowl.2 Before this battle, three companies under Robert Monckton bypassed Cap Rogue to scale tall cliffs at L'anse-au-Foulon after a 5,000-man naval landing. This was the final battle for the Marquis de Montcalm; this battle's victor, General James Wolfe, also died. For 10 points, name this decisive battle of the French and Indian War fought in 1759 on elevated fields outside a French Canadian city.", ANSWER: "Quebec"},
             {question: "2011.BBowl.2 The defending tank commander at this battle won a gold medal in equestrian jumping at the first Los Angeles Olympics. 'Howlin Mad' Holland Smith commanded one side in this battle, which saw the largest deployment in combat of (+) marines under Harry Schmidt. Tadamichi Kuribayashi had a large defensive (*) tunnel network dug before this battle. For 10 points, name this World War II battle during which Joe Rosenthal took a photo of marines raising a flag on Mount Suribachi on an island in the Pacific.", ANSWER: "Iwo Jima"},
             {question: "2012.BBowl.10 According to Susanna Dickinson's account of this battle, the commander of one side drew a line in the sand and allowed any men that crossed it to leave. That commander was (+) William Travis. This battle is not Goliad, but this battle served as inspiration for one side's victory at San Jacinto. (*) Davy Crockett and Jim Bowie were among the 189 defenders killed here. For 10 points, name this Santa Anna-led siege of a fort near San Antonio in 1836 in which the entire Texan force perished.", ANSWER: "Alamo"},
             {question: "2012.BBee.2 Mohammed Sirocco was defeated in this battle by forces whose commander died from an arrow to the eye. The forces of one side in this battle, which was fought in the Gulf of Patras, were assembled after Selim II seized Cyprus and moved into the Adriatic Sea. This battle pitted Uluj Ali against Andrea Doria and Don John of Austria. Ali Pasha was beheaded during this battle. For the point, name this 1571 naval battle that halted the expansion of the Ottoman Empire.", ANSWER: "Lepanto"},
             {question: "2012.ABowl.2 This battle ruined a campaign that began by punishing Munuza for rebelling near the Dordogne (dor-DOHN) river. The losers of this battle used heavy cavalry to charge inside a giant square formed of armorless infantry. This battle’s winner was called out by (+) Odo of Aquitaine to protect the Abbey of Saint Martin. This showdown pitted a successful (*) Mayor of the Palace against a largely Berber army under Abd-ar-Rahman al-Ghafiqi, who had to retreat across the Pyrenees. For 10 points, name this 732 CE battle at which Charles Martel halted the Muslim advance into Europe.", ANSWER: "Tours"},
             {question: "2012.ABowl.3 During this battle, one commander stood in the line of fire in order to get his brother, Humphrey, Duke of Gloucester, to safety. Thomas Erpingham led the archers in this engagement. The battleground in this battle, wet from rain the previous day, was utilized by one side's placing of stakes to combat the enemy's cavalry. The losing side during this battle was commanded by Charles d'Albret and was bogged down by the opposite side's longbows. For 10 points, name this 1415 battle during the Hundred Years' War, an English victory by Henry V.", ANSWER: "Agincourt"},
             {question: "2012.ABowl.3 The main ridge at this battle was indented by the Ohain road, and was flanked by encampments at (lah eh SONT) La Haye Sainte and the estate of (ooh-gooh-MON) Hougoumont. Prior to this engagement, one commander was drawn from the Duchess of Richmond's ball to recapture the crossroads at (+) Quatre Bras. A hastily organized Prussian force at this battle lost at (*) Ligny and was commanded by Gebhard von Blucher. For 10 points, name this 1815 battle in which the Duke of Wellington ended the Hundred Days by defeating Napoleon.", ANSWER: "Waterloo"},
             {question: "2012.ABowl.6 This battle began with an assault by Genoese mercenary crossbowmen. The winning army’s cavalry on the left flank were commanded the Earl of Arundel and the Earl of Northampton, while those on the right were led by Edward the (+) Black Prince. In this battle, the knights of Philip VI were crushed by the longbowmen of (*) Edward III. For 10 points, name this 1346 battle, a decisive victory for the English over the French in the Hundred Years War.", ANSWER: "Crecy"},
             {question: "2012.ABowl.9 This battle's winning side had their army divided into three formations of spearmen called schiltroms , which they used offensively against enemy cavalry. The victorious commander at this battle dodged the lance of Henry de Bohun before personally splitting his head with an axe. This battle began after an army arrived to reinforce Philip (+) Mowbray, who was defending Stirling Castle from a siege. The Balliols fled to Ireland after this battle, a defeat for (*) Edward II. For 10 points, name this 1314 battle where the English lost to Robert the Bruce and his Scots.", ANSWER: "Bannockburn"},
             {question: "2012.ABee.1 This battle was in part prompted by one side's commander moving his troops from Fort Moultrie to this battle's namesake location; that commander was Robert Anderson. Abner Doubleday fired the first shot for the Union in this battle, which was fought in Charleston harbor. No men on either side were killed in this battle, which was won by P.G.T. Beauregard's Confederate troops. Fought over four months after South Carolina's secession, for 10 points, name this first battle of the Civil War.", ANSWER: "Fort Sumter"},
             {question: "2012.ABee.1 As part of this attack. American prisoners of war were killed at Stoumont and Malmedy. During this offensive, George Patton declared, 'the Kraut's stuck his head in a meat grinder and I hold the handle.' During it, black soldiers were permitted to join white units by Dwight Eisenhower in an effort to prevent the Nazis from splitting the Allied forces. For the point, name this 1944-45 charge into France and Belgium, the last German offensive of World War II.", ANSWER: "Bulge"},
             {question: "2012.ABee.4 After this battle, Dumanoir was captured off of Cape Ortegal. This battle began with an attack led by Collingwood. The losing side's line was split between the Redoutable and the Bucentaure, leading to the capture of Admiral Villeneuve. Before this battle, the signal “England expects that every man will do his duty” was flown from the HMS Victory. For the point, name this victory for Horatio Nelson during the Napoleonic Wars.", ANSWER: "Trafalgar"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.4 The winning commander at this battle kept reserves on Gillies Hill. Robert Keith forced one side's archers to retreat at this battle, which saw the deaths of Robert de Clifford and the Earl of (GLAHS-ter) Gloucester. The losing side arrived at this battle in order to relieve (+) Philip Mowbray, who was besieged at Stirling Castle. One commander at this battle slew (*) Henry de Bohun with a battle axe and went on to defeat Edward II. For 10 points, name this 1314 battle in which Robert the Bruce effectively secured Scottish independence.", ANSWER: "Bannockburn"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.6 During this battle, General Roos and his force were captured after a bloody siege of redoubts. The Zaporozhian Host was defeated to deny the losing side reinforcements here. Losing at this battle forced a flight to Bendery by the traitorous Ivan Mazepa. After his forces surrendered soon after this battle, Charles XII was forced to flee to the Ottoman territory. For 10 points, name this 1709 victory for Peter I’s Russians over the Swedes in the decisive battle of the Great Northern War.", ANSWER: "Poltava"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.7 This battle included a defense of (plahnce-NWAH) Plancenoit by the count of Lobau. Preceded by an engagement at (KAT-reh BRAH) Quatre-Bras, its winners fortified the Le Haye Sainte farmhouse and the Mont-Saint-Jean escarpment. The last engagement for the Garde Imperielle under (mee-chel NAY) Michel Ney, its losers waited until noon to attack to let wet ground dry, allowing Gerhard von (BlOO-ker) Blucher's Prussians to arrive. For 10 points, name this victory in Belgium for the Duke of Wellington against Napoleon.", ANSWER: "Waterloo"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.9 One dubious account of this battle indicates that Moses Rose was the only soldier who refused to demonstrate allegiance in trying times. George Kimble provided 32 men, known as the (+) Gonzalez Rangers, at one point during this battle. A commander wrote VICTORY OR DEATH in a letter preceding this battle; that man was William (*) Travis. This victory for Santa Anna resulted in the deaths of knife-fighter James Bowie and frontiersman Davy Crockett. For 10 points, name this 1836 battle in which the namesake mission in San Antonio was overrun by Mexican soldiers during the war for Texan independence.", ANSWER: "Alamo"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.10 At one point in this battle, Louis Nolan pointed and said “There, my Lord, is your enemy,” before becoming the first casualty in one maneuver. During it, Sir Colin Campbell’s 93d Highland Regiment routed a charge in the (+) “Thin Red Line” action, while this battle’s most well-known action began after (*) Lord Raglan issued an order to attack an artillery battery that was misinterpreted as a frontal assault on a different battery. For 10 points, name this October 1854 battle in the Crimean War, best known for the ill-fated British “Charge of the Light Brigade.”", ANSWER: "Balaclava"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.11 During this battle, a foraging party led by Banastre Tarleton encountered Lazun’s Legion and John Mercer’s battalion. A diagonal column of smoke is in the background of a John Trumbull painting depicting the aftermath of this battle. French troops at this battle were led by Comte de Rochambeau, who was aided by the Marquis de Lafayette. This battle led to the signing of the Treaty of Paris. For 10 points, Lord Cornwallis lost to George Washington at what last major battle of the American Revolutionary War?", ANSWER: "Yorktown"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.12 Louis Wigfall sailed from Morris Island in an attempt to end this battle. Abner Doubleday fired the first shot for the defenders in this battle, which was preceded by Abraham Lincoln sending a letter to governor Francis W. Pickens. Its defense, led by Robert Anderson, suffered from the failure of the Star of the West to re-supply troops at the namesake locale, which was taken by P.G.T. Beauregard's forces. For 10 points, name this bombardment of a South Carolina fort that marked the beginning of the Civil War.", ANSWER: "Fort Sumter"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.14 One commander at this battle claimed that his death from wounds inflicted here could be attributed to 'missing frigates.' As it began, the Alerte unsuccessfully attempted to divert the Zealous, which attacked the (+) Guerrier. A supply of unused paint lead to the explosion of L'Orient, killing Admiral de (BRUES) Brueys. This battle occurred after (*) Napoleon's landing in Aboukir Bay. For 10 points, name this 1798 victory for the British under Horatio Nelson against a French fleet, fought near an Egyptian river.", ANSWER: "Nile"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBowl.17 During this battle, a decimated South African Brigade managed to hold onto Delville Wood, and machine gun fire repulsed a charge by lance-carrying cavalry up High Wood. At its beginning, the Allies fired 1.6 million (+) shells, many of which failed to explode on contact with barbed wire; the subsequent British charge, planned by Douglas Haig, suffered 60% casualties. This battle saw the first use of the (*) tank to break through the enemy trenches. For 10 points, name this 1916 battle, contemporaneous with Verdun, where over a million casualties occurred along the namesake French river.", ANSWER: "Somme"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBee.2 The victorious army at this battle was almost discovered by a sentry, but was able to pass as an enemy supply convoy due to the presence of a fluent French speaker. In an attempt to reverse the outcome of this battle, Francois de Levis attacked Saint-Foy. This battle was the next target after the fall of Louisbourg, and was first attempted in the unsuccessful skirmish at Beauport. It involved a force of four thousand men scaling cliffs up from the St. Lawrence River. Louis de Montcalm and James Wolfe were both killed in, for 10 points, what 1759 battle which led to the end of French Canada?", ANSWER: "Quebec"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBee.4 During this battle, an attack across the Nebel River divided the forces of Ferdinand de Marsin from the rest of army. TOne of the winning commanders in this battle had previously taken Schellenberg Fortress and was granted the royal manor of Woodstock for his victory here. This battle resulted in knocking Bavaria out of the war, and the losing commander was the Comte de Tallard. For the point, name this 1704 victory for the Duke of Marlborough and Eugene of Savoy in the War of the Spanish Succession.", ANSWER: "Blenheim"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBee.6 Victory at this battle was popular was commemorated by the square-dance tune 'The Eighth of January.' This battle actually occurred at Chalmette, downstream of the city for which it is named. A key force in this battle was the Baratarian pirates; the losers of this battle had tried to buy the help of their leader, Jean (la-FEET) Lafitte, who joined the eventual victor. This battle occurred after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent, which ended the War of 1812. For the point, name this 1815 Andrew Jackson victory, a defense of a Louisiana city.", ANSWER: "New Orleans"},
             {question: "2013.NatsBee.6 The left side of one force in this battle was commanded by Agostino Barbarigo. An advance into one side's line during this battle was countered when reserves were brought in by Alvaro de Bazan. Bazan's help during this battle also made possible the capture of the Sultana, whose commander's head was displayed on a pike. This battle fought near the Gulf of Patras was a victory for Don John of Austria, and Miguel Cervantes suffered a debilitating arm injury while fighting for the Holy Leage here. For the point, name this 1571 naval battle involving Ali Pasha's Turkish fleet.", ANSWER: "Lepanto"},
             {question: "2013.CBowl.1 In this battle, Richard Ewell's hesitation resulted in a failure to capture Culp's Hill. The losing side in this battle was deprived of important intelligence by the absence of J.E.B. Stuart's cavalry. This battle resulted from an attempt to capture a shoe factory. For 10 points, what July 1863 battle included a failed Confederate assault on Cemetery Ridge called Picket's Charge in Pennsylvania?", ANSWER: "Gettysburg"},
             {question: "2013.CBowl.2 The losing commander in this battle had suffered large casualties at Bennington two months prior. Tadeusz Kosciuzsko constructed defensive placements at Bemis Heights during this battle, where Benedict Arnold led an American attack. John Burgoyne's military career ended with a surrender to Horatio Gates here. For 10 points, name this early American victory fought in 1777 in upstate New York.", ANSWER: "Saratoga"},
             {question: "2013.CBowl.3 This battle was preceded by the Comte de Grasse's victory over Thomas Graves at the Battle of the Chesapeake. The Comte de Rochambeau gave crucial reinforcements at this engagement, which ended the Marquis de Lafayette's pursuit of this battle's loser. Charles Cornwallis surrendered after this battle. For 10 points, name this final battle of the American Revolution.", ANSWER: "Yorktown"},
             {question: "2013.CBowl.5 Following a surprise nighttime attack by the defenders in this battle, American forces retreated to the Chalmette Plantation. In this battle, Americans thwarted the efforts of the British under General Edward (+) Pakenham, losing only eight men under Old Hickory in exchange for more than two (*) thousand British. For 10 points, name this battle from the War of 1812, which, due to communications delays, took place after the treaty ending the war was signed.", ANSWER: "New Orleans"},
             {question: "2013.BBowl.1 At the beginning of this battle, Colonel Charles A. Wikoff was shot and killed. It was preceded by the capture of El Caney (cuh-NAY). Jules Garsche Ord led the charge of the (+) Buffalo Soldiers of the 10th Cavalry in this battle; simultaneously, John Pershing helped capture (*) Kettle Hill. This battle was immediately followed by a siege of Santiago. For 10 points, name this battle which made the fame of Theodore Roosevelt and the Rough Riders during the Spanish-American War.", ANSWER: "San Juan Hill"},
             {question: "2013.BBowl.4 This battle was preceded by a defeat at Bordeaux of Eudes (YOO-dayz) the Great, who joined this battle to fight against Abd al Rahman's Umayyad forces. The winning commander in this battle was given a name meaning 'hammer.' For 10 points, name this victory for Charles Martel and the Franks, which is credited with stopping a Muslim invasion into Europe from Spain in 732.", ANSWER: "Tours"},
             {question: "2013.BBowl.4 James Wilkinson was sent to inform Congress about victory during this battle. The losing general at this battle was a playwright who wrote The Maid of the Oaks. That general's initial victory at (+) Freeman's Farm here was erased by defeat at its second phase, Bemis Heights, and Benedict Arnold lost command to Horatio (*) Gates during this battle. John Burgoyne’s defeat here prompted the French to join the American cause. For 10 points, name this turning point of the American Revolution.", ANSWER: "Saratoga"},
             {question: "2013.BBowl.8 A Frederic Edwin Church painting inspired by this event was called Our Banner in the Sky. Immediately prior to it, the ship (+) Star of the West failed to reinforce. The only loss of life during this event was a gun explosion during the surrender ceremonies. It ended when Major Robert Anderson surrendered to (*) P.G.T. Beauregard. For 10 points, name this event involving the bombardment of a fort near Charleston that began the American Civil War.", ANSWER: "Fort Sumter"},
             {question: "2012.BBowl.10 According to Susanna Dickinson's account of this battle, the commander of one side drew a line in the sand and allowed any men that crossed it to leave. That commander was (+) William Travis. This battle is not Goliad, but this battle served as inspiration for one side's victory at San Jacinto. (*) Davy Crockett and Jim Bowie were among the 189 defenders killed here. For 10 points, name this Santa Anna-led siege of a fort near San Antonio in 1836 in which the entire Texan force perished.", ANSWER: "Alamo"},
             {question: "2013.BBee.1 After this battle, Gytha (GITH-uh) offered a large ransom for the body of her son. This battle came a month after Harald Hardrada and Tostig were defeated at Stamford Bridge by Harold Godwinson, who himself supposedly died at this battle when an arrow went into his eye. This battle and the events preceding it, such as the death of Edward the Confessor, are depicted on the Bayeux Tapestry. For the point, identify this 1066 battle, the keystone of William of Normandy's conquest of England.", ANSWER: "Hastings"},
             {question: "2013.BBee.1 A memorial to this battle is located on Mamayev Hill. Erich von Manstein was unable to relieve one side in this battle, which included Operation Uranus. The defense in this battle was commanded by Vasily Chuikov (chuh-WEE-kov). Friedrich Paulus was promoted to field marshal during this battle with a reminder that no German officer of that rank had ever surrendered. For the point, name this decisive World War II battle that saw over two million casualties in a southwestern Soviet city.", ANSWER: "Stalingrad"},
             {question: "2013.BBee.3 tle of Iwo Jima, and its violence may have prompted use of the atomic bombs. For the point, name this April to June 1945 battle which resulted in the highest number of casualties in World War II's Pacific theater.", ANSWER: "Okinawa"},
             {question: "2013.ABowl.2 Shortly before this battle, Odo the Great appealed to the side that won for help after a defeat at Bordeaux. The victor of this battle was given a nickname meaning 'the Hammer,' and it was a loss for Abd el-Rahman. For 10 points, name this battle where Charles Martel established the limit of Muslim advance into Western Europe.", ANSWER: "Tours"},
             {question: "2013.ABee.4 A commander at this battle refused to send Louis Davout (dah-VOO) around the left, instead sending Davout straight into the enemy's arrowhead-shaped salients known as 'fleches.' The victor of this battle refused to commit the Imperial Guard, though Peter Bagration died in the initial assault. Mikhail Kutuzov lost this battle, but the victors found Moscow empty. For the point, name this bloodiest day of the Napoleonic Wars, the climactic battle of Napoleon's invasion of Russia.", ANSWER: "Borodino"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBowl.1 During this battle, Westphalian troops captured the village of Utitsa at the southern end of the defensive lines. Defensive positions in this battle included the Raevski Redoubt and the (+) Bagration Fleches. Before this battle, Barclay de Tolly was replaced as commander of the defending side by (*) Kutuzov. The victor here refused to commit his Imperial Guard, allowing Alexander I's army to retreat and regroup. For 10 points, name this bloody 1812 battle fought west of Moscow during the Napoleonic invasion of Russia.", ANSWER: "Borodino"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBowl.13 Reportedly, a commander in this battle was saved when his pet marmoset grabbed a grenade and threw it back at the enemy. The losing side in this battle was trapped at Scropha Point, and Sebastiano Venier was elected Doge after his success bere. This battle was prompted by the public flaying of Marco Antonio Bragadin at the siege of (+) Famagusta. Its winning commander, an illegitimate son of Charles V, commanded the Real (ray-AHL). At this battle, fought in the Gulf of Patras, (*) Ali Pasha lost to Don John of Austria. For 10 points, name this 1571 victory for the Holy League over the Ottomans.", ANSWER: "Lepanto"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBowl.15 This battle started with the advance of Italian crossbowmen under Carlo Grimaldi. The victorious side in this battle followed it with a siege of Calais. The blind John of Bohemia died during this battle, in which Charles II of Alencon also died. This defeat for Philip VI of France was where the opposing commander's son won his spurs. For 10 points, name this early battle during the Hundred Years' War that was a victory for Edward III and the first major battle fought in by Edward the Black Prince.", ANSWER: "Crecy"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBowl.15 Juan Escutia died at this battle after wrapping a flag around himself and jumping off a building. John Quitman captured the Belen Gate during it, leading to the retreat of Andreas Terres. During it, Robert E. Lee led troops down the (+) Veronica and San Cosme causeways. This battle was preceded by the capture of Molino del Rey and was fought at a military (*) academy where the six 'Boy Heroes' died. This battle turned when Nicolas Bravo's garrison was defeated by Winfield Scott. For 10 points, identify this September 1847 American victory at a castle outside Mexico City.", ANSWER: "Chapultepec"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBowl.16 At this battle, the south end of a hill was held by Spier Spencer, who died here alongside Major Joseph Daviess by Burnett Creek. Prior to this battle, acting governor John Gibson recalled the eventual victor home. This battle's victors, who included the Yellow Jackets, burned nearby Prophetstown after ammo ran low among Tenskwatawa's raiders. For 10 points, name this 1811 battle in which the brother of Tecumseh lost to Indiana governor William Henry Harrison.", ANSWER: "Tippecanoe"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBee.1 Benjamin Williams was honored for valor during this battle, which took place in the state Williams later became governor of. John Macleod repelled the 1st Maryland regiment after being attacked in the woods by William Washington's forces during this battle. As it began, Banastre Tarleton fought Light Horse Harry Lee near the New Garden Meeting house. This battle slowed British advancement in the South and was thus a Pyrrhic victory by Cornwallis over Nathanael Greene. For the point, name this Revolutionary War battle fought near Greensboro, North Carolina.", ANSWER: "Guilford Courthouse"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBee.2 In a skirmish at this battle, a foraging party led by Banastre Tarleton clashed with Lauzun's Legion. The losing commander at this battle sent Charles O'Hara to surrender his sword. The losing army marched away from this battle playing 'The World Turned Upside Down' on their fifes. Tench Tlighman reported the victory at this battle to Congress, and Lord North proclaimed, 'Oh God, it's all over' when told of this battle's result. For the point, name this battle where Charles Cornwallis surrendered to George Washington.", ANSWER: "Yorktown"},
             {question: "2014.NatsBee.Finals This battle was decided with the timely arrival of William Washington's cavalry, and it is a rare example of a double envelopment. Andrew Pickens's militia and John Eager Howard's Continental soldiers participated in this battle, in which one side mocked calls for mercy by noting the opposing commander's lack of quarter at the Battle of Camden. For the point, name this 1781 battle of the Revolutionary War in which forces under Daniel Morgan defeated Banastre Tarleton's British troops in the namesake South Carolina grazing grounds.", ANSWER: "Cowpens"},
             {question: "USHB.2 This battle’s losing commander lost numerous men before it started because got diarrhea from eating green corn. This battle shattered the reputation of the victor of Saratoga, resulting in his replacement in the south by Nathanael Greene. What was this August 1780 battle in which Lord Cornwallis humiliatingly routed a larger force under Horatio Gates near a South Carolina city?", ANSWER: "Camden"},
             {question: "USHB.2 After this battle, Marcus Reno was accused of drunkenness and cowardice. This battle began with the slaying of Chief Gall's family members, and it took less than a half hour, ending with companies E, F, and C slaughtered on a hilltop. What was this June 1876 battle in Montana Territory in which the 7th Cavalry was decimated by American Indians led by Crazy Horse?", ANSWER: "Little Bighorn"},
             {question: "USHB.4 This battle’s winning side lost about a third of a militia group called the Yellow Jackets. This battle was followed a month later by the New Madrid Earthquake. This battle, which took place near “Prophetstown,” provided the nickname for the future running mate of John Tyler. What is this 1811 battle in which William Henry Harrison defeated the brother of Tecumseh?", ANSWER: "Tippecanoe"},
             {question: "USHB.5 During this battle, Lew Wallace arrived late after getting lost marching from Stoney Lonesome, while Nathan Bedford Forrest led a failed charge at Fallen Timbers. This battle featured an attack on a sunken road called the “Hornet’s Nest,” and it resulted in the death of Confederate General Albert Sidney Johnston. What was this bloodiest two-day battle of the Civil War?", ANSWER: "Shiloh"},
             {question: "USHB.6 This battle's winning commander placed his army between the Pacolet and Broad Rivers to prevent desertion. John Eager Howard won a medal for his leadership of the Maryland militia at this battle, a victory over Banastre Tarleton by Morgan's riflemen. This 1781 battle facilitated the reconquest of South Carolina. What Revolutionary War battle was fought near a town named for its pastures?", ANSWER: "Cowpens"},
             {question: "USHB.10 This battle's result was guaranteed by the failure of reinforcements under James Fannin to arrive. A letter that closed with the underlined phrase Victory or Death was written by William B. Travis during this battle. A battle cry of 'Remember [this battle]!' spurred the Americans to a victory at San Jacinto. What battle in Texas saw Santa Anna brutally murder a mission full of defenders?", ANSWER: "Alamo"},
             {question: "2014.BBowl.3 This battle marked the end of a man who had earlier survived a duel with Felix Huston. Everett Peabody accidentally started this battle ahead of schedule. The Fallen Timbers charge at this battle was led by (+) Nathan Bedford Forrest, and Lew Wallace missed most of this battle after getting lost. This battle included the charge on the (*) Hornet’s Nest and the death of Albert Sidney Johnston. For 10 points, name this 1862 Civil War battle in Tennessee.", ANSWER: "Shiloh"},
             {question: "2014.CBee.Finals People who resisted the outcome of this battle included Hereward the Wake and Edgar the Ætheling. This battle's losers had just finished a march from their defeat of Harold Hardrada at Stamford Bridge, and were led by a man who suffered an arrow to the eye at this battle, Harold Godwinson. This battle is depicted on the Bayeux Tapestry. For the point, name this 1066 battle at which William the Conqueror established Norman supremacy in England.", ANSWER: "Hastings"},
             {question: "2014.CBee.Finals This battle was made possible by blocking a join-up with George Crook at the Battle of the Rosebud. A non-participant in this battle had a vision of grasshoppers falling from the sky prior to its start. Survivors of this battle included the horse Comanche. This battle was a victory for Chief Gall and Crazy Horse against the 7th Cavalry. For the point, name this 1876 clash in Montana which destroyed the army of George Armstrong Custer.", ANSWER: "Little Bighorn"},
             {question: "2014.CBowl.4 During this battle, Strong Vincent was killed at a site where the downhill bayonet charge led by Joshua Chamberlain occurred. This battle, which included the skirmish of Little Round Top, turned on an ill-advised charge ordered by Confederate general George Pickett. For 10 points, name this July 1863 clash in Pennsylvania which was the turning point of the Civil War.", ANSWER: "Gettysburg"},
             {question: "2014.CBowl.5 During this larger operation, soldiers were executed at Chenogne (pr. chay-NON) in revenge for the earlier Malmedy (pr. mahl-may-DEE) Massacre. Anthony McAuliffe issued the singular reply (+) 'Nuts!' to a surrender demand during this operation, which was named for the (*) shape created in a map of troop lines in the Ardennes forest. For 10 points, name this late 1944 World War II initiative, the final major German offensive of the war.", ANSWER: "Bulge"},
             {question: "2014.CBowl.9 This battle turned on the use of a perpendicular two-column approach, and the few losing ships that escaped were led by Federico Gravina. Prior to this battle, a (+) semaphore message reading 'England expects that every man will do his duty' was transmitted from the (*) Victory. For 10 points, name this 1805 naval battle at which Pierre-Charles Villeneuve was defeated by Horatio Nelson, who died during the fighting and is commemorated at a namesake London square.", ANSWER: "Trafalgar"},
             {question: "2015.NatsBowl.1 During this battle, Charles Piroth committed suicide. It began with the dropping of paratroopers in Operation Castor and saw the creation of the Beatrice and Gabrielle strongpoints. The losers in this battle utilized the “hedgehog” strategy of General Navarre, which failed when opposing artillery was placed in the surrounding hills. It ended with an assault ordered by Vo Nguyen Giap. For 10 points, name this battle where a French garrison was defeated by the Viet Minh.", ANSWER: "Dien Bien Phu"},
             {question: "2015.NatsBowl.6 In this battle, Henry de Bohun attempted to charge the opposing side's leader, who promptly split de Bohun's head in half with an axe. Alexander Seton deserted one side in this battle, which featured a disastrous charge by the Earl of Gloucester (pr. GLOSS-ter), Gilbert de Clare. The victors at this battle issued the (+) Declaration of Arbroath. The schiltron formation was used to great effect by one side in this battle, which ended when (*) Edward II fled to Dunbar Castle and sailed back to England. For 10 points, name this 1314 battle in the First War of Scottish Independence, a decisive victory for Robert the Bruce.", ANSWER: "Bannockburn"},
];
